<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A particular ansvver to a book intituled, The clergy in their colours</title>
            <author>J. D. (John Davy)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 108 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37268</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D443</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14910</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11845872</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11845872</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49844</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A37268)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49844)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 24:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A particular ansvver to a book intituled, The clergy in their colours</title>
                  <author>J. D. (John Davy)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 42, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A. Miller for William Leigh ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1651.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: J.D.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to John Davy. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fry, John, 1609-1657. --  Clergy in their colours.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49844:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49844:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Particular ANSVVER TO A BOOK <hi>INTITuLED,</hi> THE CLERGY IN THEIR COLOURS.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Contra rationem nemo ſobrius, contra Scripturas nemo Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus, contra Eccleſiam nemo pacificus ſenſerit,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> lib. de <hi>Trin.</hi> c. 6.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="imprimatur">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Septemb.</hi> the 18th 1651. </p>
                        <p>Imprimatur,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>John Downam.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. Miller</hi> for <hi>William Leigh</hi> at the Turks-head in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> MDCLI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:49844:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49844:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE LOVER OF THE CLERGY <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>JOHN DAVY</hi> OF <hi>Taunton Magdalen,</hi> Perſeverance.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Uncle,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have ſent you in theſe Papers a ſalve, ſuch as by Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing on your coſt and directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I was able to compoſe for that wound which an unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved enemy hath made on the reputation of the Clergy: a wound too deep for me to ſearch, too great to cure: but having found one inſtrument that cauſed it where I now reſide, I have endeavoured to apply my medicine thereto, hoping that (as is believed of the <hi>Unguentum armarium</hi>) it may tranſmit ſome ſanative vertue to th'affected ſubject. Howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, I ſhall hereby manifeſt my reſpect unto the ſuffering Parties, and (in ſome meaſure) have performed the duty of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt obſervant Nephew,</hi> and <hi>ever gratefull Servant,</hi> J. D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="recommendation">
            <pb facs="tcp:49844:3"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have curſorily viewed this Book and think it ſeaſonable for theſe times in which the Function of the Miniſtry is ſo much oppoſed:</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, EDW. LEIGH.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49844:3"/>
            <head>TO THE AUTHOUR OF THE BOOK INTITULED <hi>The Clergie in their Colours,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F you are indeed a Member of the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> and not rather a malicious Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite, ſlily endeavouring the increaſe of our diviſions (which I ſee cauſe to ſuſpect,) Give me leave, as a free-born Engliſh-man, to declare my thoughts concerning your Boook, intituled, <hi>The Clergie in their Colours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which you begin with a profeſſion of your diſlike of ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring your ſelf under any mans wings: and no wonder; for whoſe Patronage need you deſire, who call your ſelf a Patriot of your Country? I have as little propenſity thereto as your ſelf; and yet I might juſtly be thought immodeſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable too, if I ſhould impute all Dedication of Works to diſtruſt of Workmanſhip, which you there inſinuate. The greatneſs of a mans confidence adds nothing <hi>(in facto)</hi> to the goodneſs of his actions: No doubt but you may ſee Epiſtles Dedicatory prefixed to many excellent Monuments of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and piety: Though the Art need no Patron, yet the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt may: as for example, You being a Member of Parliament, for ſo (that I may not ſpeak to no body) I muſt ſuppoſe you to be, your very name is ſufficient to commend to the world that which you have written: But ſhould ſuch an obſcure perſon as I am, ſet forth endeavours no leſs deſerving, yet could I not expect a like acceptation.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:49844:4"/>
            <q>
               <l>—Plurima ſunt, quae</l>
               <l>Non homines audent pertuſa dicere lana.</l>
            </q>
            <p>In the ſame Page you tell us that you <hi>decline the courting your Reader with a flattering Epiſtle for his approbation, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing irrational and ridiculous,</hi> &amp;c. You do well in declining flattery: but Epiſtles to the Reader are for many works ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary; and, as ridiculous as you ſuppoſe them to your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent purpoſe, you have no leſs in effect in this very Apology; for what is it other then a Preparative to your enſuing Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe? and an excuſe for not Epiſtolizing, is the very ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of many Epiſtles. So your ſecond Section, <hi>I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that many will look wiſhly upon me for this work,</hi> &amp;c. And your third, <hi>'Tis probable that many will think me pragmatical, &amp;c.</hi> have not indeed the form, but contain the matter of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles. Which I take not notice of as any great eye-ſore in it ſelf, but as from you, who criticize moſt ſeverely of any man whoſe writings are at this time in my memory.</p>
            <p>In that laſt mentioned Sect, you ſpeak of a kinde of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Idolized in <hi>England,</hi> by which you mean skill in the holy Languages, as is afterwards intimated, <hi>p.</hi> 3. <hi>l.</hi> 13. And how I pray you is that Idolized with us? An Idol properly is either that which men worſhip for a God, againſt the firſt precept of the Decalogue, or which they ſuperſtitiouſly uſe in the worſhip of God againſt the ſecond: And of theſe the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>An Idol is nothing in the world,</hi> 1 Cor. 8.4. alluding (as I ſuppoſe) to <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>inanitates,</hi> 1 Sam. 12.21. there tranſlated <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as alſo, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.29. in regard they fruſtrate the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of their confiders; there being no ſuch divine power preſent with the Idol, as againſt the firſt Commandment is ſuppoſed, no any ſuch acceptation of their exhibition in the ſervice of the true God, as is imagined by the violaters of the ſecond. Now can you call the gift of tongues lying vanities, which the Apoſtles reckons among the gifts of the Spirit? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.10. which whether inſpired by the holy Ghoſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly, or acquired by Gods bleſſing on mens induſtry, have the ſame uſe in order to their end, <hi>viz.</hi> the making known the minde of God: and how that ſhould be made known ſo far as (bleſſed be God) we underſtand it, without the holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49844:4"/>or they to us Engliſh-men, without the uſe of tongues, do but tell me, and take my Buckler. Or if you would have on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly their continuance ſuperfluous (the Scripture being already in our Vulgar Language) you will either diſcover your igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of their multifarious uſe in Expoſition, or foul ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude for the benefit you have received from them. Or if you mean Idolatry, improperly ſpoken (for your word Idolize im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies action, and ſo a culpability rather in the ſubject then the object) you then complain of their abuſe only, and ſo you may as well complain of the beſt things that are; for what is ſo good as may not be abuſed? And you might with as little abſurdity have prohibited us the quotation of holy Scriptures in defence of true Religion, becauſe reprobates wreſt them to their own deſtruction.</p>
            <p>And now give me leave to expoſtulate with you a little in the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.22. <hi>Thou that abhorreſt Idols, doeſt not thou commit ſacriledge?</hi> The calling of the Miniſtry you plainly deſpiſe, and if the perſons in eſpecial manner dedicated to God, do not eſcape you, it is not to be hoped that you will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge any, ſo much as relative holineſs in Places and Things: And if that be your judgement, I beſeech you tell me, how there can be any ſacriledge, or how that ſin which <hi>Paul</hi> there argues to be ſo bad as Idolatry, can at all be committed? But this by the way.</p>
            <p>In the third Page (for you Sections are not diſtinguiſht by figures) you aſſert, that <hi>It hath pleaſed God in all ages to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the wiſe and mighty, by poor and deſpicable inſtruments in the eyes of the world.</hi> And you call our Saviour Chriſt, his Apoſtles and Martyrs to witneſs what no good Chriſtian will deny. But what is this to your purpoſe? Will it hence follow that Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is uſeleſs in the Church of God? Becauſe God ſometimes works without means, muſt he never work with them? It was well foreſeen of you therefore, while you made an exception in your inſtance, ſaying ſome of the Prophets, and many Apoſtles; but why you ſhould put our Saviour Chriſt into your illiterate catalogue, I know not; unleſs that when it ſhall be proved im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent to the main queſtion, in this particular, you may li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it to your immediatly-foregoing aſſertion, to which you have (it may be for that cauſe) ſophiſtically annexed it. And as
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49844:5"/>for all thoſe you ſpeak of, recorded by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Fox</hi> in his Acts and Monuments, although they were children in Learning, yet they ſtood on mens ſhoulders, and might therefore ſee further then a Popiſh <hi>Polyphemus:</hi> For I hope you cannot deny God made uſe of many famous lights of Learning for illumination of the unlearned people of that time, ſome of which went to heaven in fiery Charets with them. Chriſt called indeed unlearned men, but he taught them what was neceſſary to their Apoſtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip while they preached only to the Jews, and that within the limits of their own Country, where the Hebrew tongue was well enough underſtood, as appears, <hi>Acts</hi> 21.40. although they uſed the <hi>Syrian</hi> Dialect: But after our Saviour his Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when they were to teach all Nations, the gift of Tongues as thereto requiſite, was conferred upon them. And as Manna ceaſed when the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> came into the Land of <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an;</hi> ſo extraordinary gifts ceaſed, when God had by ordinary provided for the propagation of Religion. So that to inhibit the uſe of learning in our Preachers of the Goſpel, were as irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional, as to have forbidden the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> eating the fruits of <hi>Canaan,</hi> becauſe they had Manna in the Wilderneſs.</p>
            <p>Preſently after, you make an odious parallel with Romiſh Wolves and Presbyterian Paſtors, affirming that as they, ſo theſe hold it dangerous for ſuch people to breath, by whom their pomp and gallantry is like to fall. Now Sir, I require you to prove this bloudy accuſation, and to make it appear that the Grandees of the Presbyterian faction (as you call them) bare ſuch mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall hatred againſt any people in <hi>England,</hi> for Religions ſake, as the Popiſh Prieſts in Q. <hi>Maries</hi> daies had againſt all people of reformed Religion, or elſe I ſhall hold you guilty of a mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious untruth for ſo ſpeaking. And yet as if this were a ſmall matter to make them homicides, you would make them mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers of ſouls too, by affirming, that <hi>As the Popiſh Clergie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard the common people from reading the Scriptures; ſo theſe had rather people ſpent their time in reading of tales, or following their worldly affairs, but when they are hearing them ſpeaking contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions,</hi> &amp;c. Now I am ſure that I am compaſſed about with clouds of witneſſes, who will teſtifie with me, that we never found cauſe of ſuch ſuſpition: but the Miniſters of the Goſpel do alwaies exhort to reading and meditation of the Word of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49844:5"/>God: or if any ſuch had been, we have not wanted time and means enough to diſplace them ſince the beginning of this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. Yet ſtill your charge runs generally againſt the Clergy, as if <hi>quatenus</hi> Clergy they were the greateſt enemies to the Church of God. And yet if you were not over-biaſſed with prejudice you would confeſs with me that the ſame men you inveigh againſt have been the inſtruments of what good God hath wrought in your ſoul, either by their word or writings. Good Sir, do but examine, when did you firſt come out of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and by what means? and do not with <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> his Hart, crop that buſh in a calm that ſheltred you in a ſtorm. Or if it be not true by your ſelf, yet ſure it is that multitudes of gracious ſouls will acknowledge men of that calling for their ghoſtly Fathers. And what greater ſeal of an Apoſtleſhip can be deſired then what the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.2. in theſe words, <hi>If I am not an Apoſtle to others, doubtleſs I am one to you, for the ſeal of my Apoſtleſhip are ye in the Lord.</hi> As therefore that Potentate ſaid of his government, Call it what you will, but by it I keep the people in good order: So may I ſay of the calling of the Miniſters amongſt us, Call it you what you pleaſe, I am ſure the word in their mouth, is, by the grace of God accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying it, made the power of God unto ſalvation. This is it that excited me, otherwiſe ſtudious of obſcurity, to make my ſelf (I know not yet how) publique ſpectacle, and <hi>Aegles</hi>-like, to force nature upon the ſight of injurious dealing: for I am nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Parſon, Vicar nor Curate, and might notwithſtanding any private intereſt have been ſilent: but the Cauſe is Gods, on whom I depend, and may therefore ſay with the Lepers, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 7.9. I do not well to hold my peace. And indeed ſhould the redeemed of the Lord, that have had the knowledge and love of God wrought in them by our publique Miniſtry be ſilent, when ſuch indignities are caſt upon it, it were enough to make, as our Saviour ſaith in the Goſpel, the ſtones to cry, that I may not ſay, to cry out againſt them, and to condemn their ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude.</p>
            <p>In <hi>page</hi> 4. you carp at the diſtinction of <hi>Clergie</hi> and <hi>Laity,</hi> but for what reaſon we may go look: though things in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves be diſtinct by nature, yet they cannot in diſcourſe be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed without ſeveral names; whereof your own practice
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49844:6"/>gives experience in the title of your Book, <hi>viz. The Clergie in their Colours;</hi> which if you ſay was done for diſtinctions ſake, that we might know of whom you ſpeak, as <hi>p.</hi> 45. grant us the ſame liberty, and we ask no more. It's a queſtion whether you know how the firſt of your family came by his name, and yet you will think it cannot with juſtice be taken from you: But the Clergy have beſides Antiquity, Etymologie for their name; being ſo called from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a Lot, becauſe they are inſtead of the Levites, the Lot of Gods and God of their Inheritance, in eſpecial manner; for in a larger ſenſe it is applied to all the faithfull, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.3. and ſo are the Saints called Prieſts too, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though not by their particular but general calling of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity: and ſo all the Lords people might without offence be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led holy; but yet when theſe ſame words were uſurped by <hi>Ko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah</hi> in oppoſition to the holineſs of the Prieſts Office, God pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed that ſchiſm of his with a ſtranger ſchiſm of the earth that ſwallowed him up. Nor is the word therefore leſs perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, becauſe Clergy-men are not now choſen by a <hi>ſortilegium,</hi> as was <hi>Matthias;</hi> for Apoſtles were a diſtinct degree of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and to be choſen by God himſelf. But however, we are not ſo much in uſuall words to regard <hi>a quo,</hi> as <hi>ad quid;</hi> and in every Art we muſt keep the ſame terms it hath been expreſt in aforetime, or elſe we can neither underſtand, nor be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood. <hi>My lot is faln to me in a fair ground,</hi> ſaith <hi>David.</hi> Pſal. 16. alluding to the manner of dividing the land of <hi>Canaan</hi> to the twelve Tribes; and by like Analogie is <hi>Cyrus</hi> cal'd Gods anointed, and yet we do not ſuppoſe the <hi>Perſians</hi> to have had any ſuch ceremony as anointing in their Kings Inauguration. And as for the other member of the diſtinction <hi>(Laity)</hi> he that knoweth no more of the primitive Church then the beginning and end of their Liturgy, may there ſee <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which in neither place can be ſynthetically taken; for the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter did not keep ſilence, but the people, nor was he both the diſmiſſer and the diſmiſſed. But howſoever you quarrel with the name, it is the thing that troubles you, the very Office it ſelf. It was once threatned for a judgement, that there ſhould be like people like Prieſt, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.9. But you are not ſatisfied with likeneſs, but muſt have them the very ſame. From which errour if neither the fearfull puniſhment of <hi>Kora, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiram</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:49844:6"/>in the wilderneſs, of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zza</hi> before the Temple built, of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzia</hi> in the Temple, deter you; nor the practice of the Apoſtle in ordaining Miniſters, and making their Office antitype to the Prieſt's Office in the Law, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.13, 14. and 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17, 18. neither the practice of the Church of God in all ages, nor the Churches being upheld to this day by that Miniſtry, convince you, I know not to what purpoſe I ſhould inſiſt longer on this particular, nor can I conceive to what end you reade the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture. We expected a Reformation according to the Word of God, and the example of the Primitive Church: but let it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear that either of them will allow of your opinion, and I will with humility and ſincerity of heart go to <hi>Pauls</hi> Croſs (if ſuch a place there be in <hi>London</hi>) and there ſing a Palinodie for this my errour.</p>
            <p>In the ſame Page you charge them with <hi>contradictions and ſtrange divinity, ſuch as they have taken upon truſt from Antient and Modern Writers,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Claudius accuſat maechos:</hi> for how can that be ſtrange Divinity, which your ſelf confeſs to be found in Antient and Modern Writers? But examine what Authours you will, you ſhall be found in this opinion a ſtranger to them all. You need not therefore fear (what you ſeem to doubt of, <hi>p.</hi> 9.) that your <hi>reſpondent</hi> would bumbaſt his diſcourſe with al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legations out of divers Authors, ſeeing all that you expect may be diſpatcht in one ſyllable, which is, <hi>ALL.</hi> But how any man can without braſen impudence oppoſe his private conceptions to the unanimouſly received verdicts of all Churches in all ages, comes not within the verge of my apprehenſion. Then follows, <hi>Of which their Studies are full, and without which they dare not appear the next Sunday in the Pulpit.</hi> Some Studies are indeed well repleniſht, and if all were ſo it would be ſo much the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: but a charitable Chriſtian would from hence gather that ſuch men ſpend as well as are ſpent in the duties of their calling, and how much more is expended in this kinde ſo much the more doth it argue their converſation to be without covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. But <hi>they dare not,</hi> &amp;c. How know you that? What then makes them ſo ready in divine diſcourſes on all occaſions? But you have a clear proof of it. And what's that? <hi>If they be from home and are ſpoken to to preach, you muſt excuſe them,</hi> &amp;c. Which argues not dependance of a Library in any candid judgement,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49844:7"/>but rather deſire of ſufficient premeditation, that they may not do the work of the Lord negligently. Is it not their ſet duty to labour in the Word and Doctrine? <hi>Dabitur in hora</hi> was an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary gift for extraordinary times: What, no more but up and preach? I had thought praier before ſtudy, conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſtate of the people to hear, a ſubject ſelected for that purpoſe, method moſt making for edification, with appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the doctrine excogitated to the Preachers ſelf firſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> had been requiſite; all which in a ſtrange place cannot ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be well effected. Then follows immediatly, <hi>And yet for all this they as confidently obtrude themſelves upon the people to tell,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>as thoſe that have the immediat aſſiſtance of the holy Ghoſt,</hi> &amp;c. What did they excuſe themſelves for not preaching, and yet for all that obtrude their Sermons to the people? How can both be true? unleſs you mean at ſome other time, for you do not ſay ſo. And who they are that have immediate aſſiſtance, in that ſenſe you deliver it, I know not: but ſure I am there be ſome Preachers who compoſe their Sermons without any other preſent help of Books then the holy Scriptures; who yet will acknowledge themſelves to be but as Muſhrums in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon with many Cedars for ability, againſt whom you belch out that ſcandalous accuſation.</p>
            <p>In the fifth Page you ſeem to travell with diſcoveries which people were not yet able to bear: of whom you have never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs a tender reſpect in regard God is good to his Saints under a variety of diſpenſation, and they ſweetly enjoy him. And why will you not give the people of God leave to enjoy his preſence under what diſpenſation God hath placed them? Why do you call them a poor deluded people, if you acknowledge their enjoyment of God in their preſent condition? And if it were poſſible for them to relinquiſh their ſtation, whither would you carry them, what can you promiſe them, and what ſecurity will you give them for performance if you promiſe any thing? Strange it is to me that you ſhould acknowledge the the bleſſed condition of the people, and yet cry down the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters under the ſame dispenſation; How ſhort herein do you come of <hi>Joſeph Salmon</hi> himſelf? He profeſſeth himſelf above forms, and yet to ſuch as are under that diſpenſation doth not diſallow them: you acknowledge Ordinances, and endeavour
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49844:7"/>their deſtruction; for what is it leſs to grant a publique wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip without the Miniſtry, then as that mercileſs deceiver <hi>D. D' Alva</hi> did, who promiſed life to his priſoners, but would allow them nothing wherewith to preſerve it? Should all they whom you call Clergie be excluded, how many miles might a man travell to hear a Sermon? Truly Sir, your writing diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers you to be a man ſubject to like paſſion with other men, and having begun to ſpeak, I ſhould but flatter you in concealing it. You tell us indeed but in the ſixth Page, that you <hi>take no pleaſure to caſt dirt in mens faces,</hi> and promiſe much tenderneſs, love and meekneſs: but how well you perform it, let the next Page witneſs; where taking occaſion to blame M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Cheynell</hi> for foul-mouth'd language, as <hi>Diogenes</hi> trampled on <hi>Plato's</hi> Pallat with greater pride then ever was uſed in it; ſo you do the ſame by him which you reprehend in him. What elſe mean theſe words, <hi>Sign in Aries and Cockoe moneth?</hi> Was the man ſo cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie that he might not be anſwered, and yet might he be flouted? Give me rather (if I muſt have one) a railing <hi>Rabſhakeh,</hi> then a ſcoffing <hi>Michol:</hi> Virulencie of ſpeech many times whets the ſpirits of Gods people, and makes their zeal more fervent: but scoffing hath commonly, as it were, an inchanting power of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numming the affections, as experience teacheth us. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not unlikely it is that the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.36. ranks mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with ſcourging; and if we compare, <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.9. with <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.29. we ſhall finde mocking called perſecution. You ſpake but a little before of your being carried out by the ſpirit of the Lord: and now I pray you Sir, conſider whether theſe words be congruous to the ſpirit of God or no; yea (whatſoever you may think of them) to common ſenſe: for what means <hi>The ſign in Aries?</hi> I had thought Aries had been a Sign, what was the ſign in the ſign? Truly Sir, if you did it ignorantly, you were more bold then wiſe: if wilfully, I know no ground for your confidence, unleſs as the Pope ſaid he would pronounce <hi>Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra, in contemptum Grammaticorum,</hi> ſo you calling your ſelf a Parliament man, think you may ſpeak <hi>non</hi>-ſenſe by authority. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. O <hi>Thales, Thales,</hi> quoth an old Wife, how thinkeſt thou to comprehend the things in heaven, and canſt not ſee what is before thy feet? when he going a Star-gazing fell into a pit:
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49844:8"/>So how do you think to perſwade us that you are wiſer then all the Learned of paſt and preſent ages, while we finde you ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling in the very <hi>A.B.C.</hi> of an Almanack? Or if your wiſdom be only ſpiritual and not carnal, why do you thus <hi>miſcere ſacra profanis,</hi> and having begun in the ſpirit, proceed in the fleſh? What cauſe you have to accuſe M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Cheynel</hi> of madneſs, I know not, for I never heard of the man but by your relation: but never (till now) did I know any man well in his wits, condemn men for Droans by reaſon of their induſtry, as you have done, <hi>p.</hi> 8. for what leſs then induſtry doth reading and writing of vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminous diſcourſes ſignifie.</p>
            <p>Then with a Sarcaſticall reproach you aſſault the <hi>Aſſembly of Divines, as,</hi> you ſay, <hi>they are called.</hi> What will not a man of a malignant ſpirit carp at? A Profeſſor of Mathematicks is cal'd a Mathematician, of Logick a Logician, of Rhetorick a Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torician; and why muſt not a Profeſſor of Divinity be cal'd a Divine? O baſe envie! for what elſe can any man ſay in ſuch an exception? And what in your Ironical accuſation do you finde culpable in them? but that <hi>In ſeven or eight years time, with the help of the Kirk of</hi> Scotland, <hi>they bring forth only a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſm, and Annotations on the Bible:</hi> whom yet <hi>Telephus</hi> like you heal as it were with the ruſt of the ſame weapon; for anon, <hi>p.</hi> 29. you charge them with being able to do nothing without leave from the Parliament. Now whether the <hi>Egyptians</hi> dealt worſe with the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in giving them no ſtraw and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding them to make brick, or you with that Aſsembly, in binding their hands, and complaining of their idleneſs, let the world judge. If I had heard of nothing done by them, yet they deſerve too reverent opinion of me to be thought idle: and I have heard their Annotations commended by ſome, who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably, can judge as well as you; and would therefore think it extream impudence in any man to affirm with you, <hi>If none be the worſe for it, few are the better.</hi> And when we look for a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon hereof in the next words, there is nothing but <hi>Experto crede Roberto:</hi> Which when I firſt ſaw, I turned back to the Title page to ſee if your name were <hi>Robert,</hi> that ſo I might have an aſſeveration of at leaſt one mans experience; but it might be <hi>Robin Hood</hi> for any thing thence to be collected, for him you have up too <hi>p.</hi> 4. I marvel with what face you charge Preachers
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49844:8"/>with bold obtruſion of their doctrine, and your ſelf ſo magiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rially require our aſſent to your calumnies on no better account then <hi>Experto crede Roberto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for your following complaint of their <hi>wary handling or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable prolixity in explaining Scriptures:</hi> I have no more to ſay to it, but that if ſome be leſs able, they be the more wiſe in being wary. The Scriptures are as a water in which as a Lamb may wade, ſo an Elephant may ſwim: <hi>Who is ſufficient for theſe things?</hi> ſaith the bleſſed Apoſtle, of the Miniſteriall Office, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.16. But (thanks be to God for them) we have many that handle not the Word of God deceitfully, but ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Workmen that need not be aſhamed: the undervaluing of whoſe labours, conſidering what good God hath wrought by them, may give us juſt cauſe to fear, that he will in juſtice de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive us of them.</p>
            <p>In <hi>p.</hi> 10. you ſay that for ſome years paſt, you <hi>have entred into a ſerious conſideration of your later end,</hi> &amp;c. And ſo no doubt have many others, and the further they have proceeded in that meditation, the more heartily they have embraced the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpel. But <hi>on ſearch of the Scriptures you finde con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions, abſurdities and inconſequencies,</hi> &amp;c. You might have done well in ſhewing us what doctrines held forth by our Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters were repugnant to the Word of God; which you have not done here, nor in the remainder of your diſcourſe; as I might make appear now, but for inverting the order begun. But how comes it to paſs that the further you ſeek the more you are intangled, while the more we ſearch, the more we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed? But, as a wiſe man of this Nation ſaid concerning Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, A little might make a man an Atheiſt, a great deal might make him a Divine: ſo in matters of this nature, men of the ſhalloweſt apprehenſions are the greateſt gain-ſayers: For among many ſuch complainers of contradictions I have not yet found one, who in its Logicall propriety, could tell what a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction was. I cannot ſay that ever I heard falſe doctrine in a publique Sermon in my life time, and yet (I am bound to thank God for it) I have of a childe been inſtructed in the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments of Religion; theſe hear it in every Sermon; and yet when I come to reaſoning with them, they and I are in the points controverted altogether of the ſame opinion. But as <hi>Icte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricorum
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49844:9"/>oculis omnia flava,</hi> ſo they having a ſpirit of contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in them, may imagine all that they reade or hear to be full of contradiction.
<q>Omnia perverſas poſſunt corrumpere mentes.</q> As <hi>Harpaſte</hi> complained of the darkneſs of the houſe when her eye-ſight fail'd her: Or as too indulgent parents complain of the Schoolmaſters negligence, when their own foſtering their children in untowardneſs is the cauſe of their <hi>non</hi>-proficience: ſo do theſe men father upon the publique Ordinances the ſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious brats of their own inventions. Who but theſe complain of pudling the waters of the Sanctuary by confuſed preaching, and talk of new lights, and ſtrange revelation? who had they but an impartiall eie to their own condition, would rather com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of the darkneſs of their own underſtanding.</p>
            <p>In <hi>p.</hi> 12. you tell us how hardly people could be drawn from the good opinion they have of their Teachers, and the Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers themſelves Pope-like will not ſubmit for many inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. To what, I pray you, ſhould they ſubmit? for you do not tell us what? Should the Moon ſtay her courſe becauſe a Wolf barks at her? Or the builders of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> deſiſt from their labour, becauſe <hi>Sanballat</hi> and <hi>Tobia</hi> mock at their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding? Doth Chriſt teach us to pray the Lord of the harveſt to ſend forth more labourers into his harveſt, and muſt they that are entred withdraw themſelves upon your malevolent perſwaſion? Muſt the Vineyard of the Lord of Hoſts be left like the field of <hi>Solomons</hi> ſluggard? What, be there no ſouls ſtill to be cal'd home by the preaching of the word, none to be confirmed, none to be comforted? O Sir, whatever you boaſt of your own experience, had you ever been truly ſenſible of a naturall condition, felt the dolorous throws of a new birth, and apprehended the ſoul-raviſhing comfort of Gods Spirit ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing true peace to your conſcience, which by this deſpiſed preaching is daily wrought in the hearts of Gods choſen, you would ſay with them, <hi>How beautifull are the feet of them that preach the Goſpel of peace, and bring glad tidings of good things?</hi> and with the beleeving <hi>Galatians</hi> be ready to pull out your eies for them, whoſe eies you would rather have pulled out. Witneſs your envying their <hi>Profit</hi> and <hi>Credit,</hi> while you af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm them to have no right to either. Nor is it a Tithe matter
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49844:9"/>you talk of (though that but for covetouſneſs ſake need not have been queſtioned) but <hi>p.</hi> 13. you allow them not the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nevolence of the people and ſo would at once rob them of their reſpect and maintenance, and the people alſo of that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berality that might redound to their account in the day of the Lord. But why have they no right to either? As for their Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>They that labour in the word and doctrine are to be accounted worthy of double honour:</hi> It's worthy our ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation that Honour is here ſubjected in the people, as being their duty to give it, <hi>Are to be accounted;</hi> for <hi>Honor eſt in hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rante non in honorato,</hi> ſo that if it be the peoples duty to give it, here is honour compleat, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. It will be long ere you envy their pains if you hold in this minde; who might there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore anſwer you, as <hi>Marius</hi> is by <hi>Saluſt</hi> in his <hi>Jugurthine</hi> war, brought in ſpeaking to the people of <hi>Rome; Invident honori meo, ergo invideant labori, innocentiae, periculis etiam meis, quoniam per haec illam cepi.</hi> And for their maintenance they have ſuch evidence as no man can ſhew for any other inheritance; mens laws may alter, and Proprieties be Impropriated, but God's more ſure then that of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians</hi> altereth not. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.14. <hi>The Lord hath ordained that they which preach the Goſpel ſhould live of the Goſpel:</hi> And from the ſixth verſe of that Chapter to the fourteenth he argueth to the ſame purpoſe. And the Spirit of God foreſeeing what ſhifts men were like to invent, whereby to debar Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters from their due, and themſelves from their duty, adds an eſpecial caveat to that precept, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6. as worthy M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Dyke (quem honoris cauſa nomino)</hi> in his eximious Tractate of the hearts deceitfulneſs hath obſerved, <hi>Cap.</hi> 17. <hi>p.</hi> 234. for having ſaid in the ſixth verſe, <hi>Let him that is taught in the word make him that taught him partaker of all his goods,</hi> to prevent ſuch witty excuſes as might hinder the ſincerity of performance of that duty, he adds in the ſeventh verſe, <hi>Be not deceived, God is not mocked.</hi>— Beſides, it were unreaſonable, 1. That they who are imployed for us ſhould not be maintained by us, <hi>The labourer is worthy of his hire.</hi> It was ſpoken by our Lord to them who took no more pains for preaching but to travel and ſpeak, and not to ſtudy as theſe do. 2. That ſo much expence as is requiſit to fit men for the Miniſtry ſhould have no recompence.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49844:10"/>A man that hath ſerved an Apprenticeſhip ſeven years hath a Calling to live on, but he that hath ſpent three times ſeven in Study, ſhall by your allowance have no reward for all his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of monies, time, or labour: which how it can ſtand with that royall Law and conſent of all civilized people, <hi>To do as we would be done by,</hi> let any reaſonable man judge. Perhaps you will ſay they are not the men, or they have ſome other ill quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication rendring them incapable of what privilege otherwiſe were aſſigned to them. Why? but theſe are the Diſpenſers of the Word and Sacraments, theſe are they that watch over our ſouls; it is by their Miniſtry that God convinceth, converteth, confirmeth his people, and to whom elſe can it be applied? You complain of defects in the execution of their Office; be it gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; yet let them have therewithall the allowance due to all mortall men (from us at leaſt) and they may paſs for currant in the balance of a Chriſtian judgement. Very hainous were the ſins of <hi>Ely</hi>'s ſons, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.22, 24. and yet the people are held guilty of ſin for abhorring the offering of the Lord. And Chriſt made great complaint of them who ſat in <hi>Moſes</hi> chair in his time, who yet commands the people to hear and obey them, whom yet he convinceth of errours in the doctrine it ſelf, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. Is it not ſtrange reaſoning, that becauſe a man is not yet near his journies end he ſhould therefore ſit down and go no further? and yet what leſs doth this ſound, Becauſe our Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters have not yet attained to ſo clear knowledge of the minde of God in Scripture, as to hold it forth ſo diſtinctly as ſome of the people do, or at leaſt think they do underſtand it; let there therefore be no more Study and no more preaching? Why? how then ſhall we come by more knowledge? you ſay by ſearching the Scriptures: one might think then the Eunuch ſhould have had no great need of <hi>Philip.</hi> 'Tis true indeed (as <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid) no matter if all our books were burnt, ſo the holy Scriptures were well learned, and rightly underſtood: but do you by bare reading, meditation and comparing Scripture with Scripture, without any help of tongues and other Hiſtories, give a ſatisfactory anſwer to many queſtions, to which the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures give occaſion of enquiry, <hi>Et eris mihi magnus Apollo:</hi> I will acknowledge you then with <hi>Apollos</hi> in the Acts to be a man mighty in the Scriptures indeed. Or if this might be ſuppoſed
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49844:10"/>by your ſelf, yet we know ſome men will not, many men cannot, moſt men do not ſpend ſo much time about them: and if your own conſcience might ſpeak freely, it would confeſs, That for the knowledge you have attained to in Divinity, you are, next to God, beholden to the labours of the Clergy.</p>
            <p>But <hi>p.</hi> 13. <hi>This would abate the heat of Parſons kitchens, and hinder their families from following faſhions,</hi> &amp;c. And would it not alſo abate the heat of charity in giving, and of nature in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny indigent receivers, who from the Parſons moſt commonly receive moſt liberall contributions? The Apoſtle ſaith, A Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop muſt be given to hoſpitality: but you are ſo far from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting to his exerciſe of hoſpitality, that you allow not other men to be hoſpitable to him. And as for faſhions, I think no man (but in ſome cauſes extraordinary) ought to be ſingular; the fault is therefore chiefly in the firſt inventer. But the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, the Clergy (for there be but few of them Parſons in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon with the reſt) they are in all the fault: As the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens were uſed to ſay of the Chriſtians, when any gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall calamity befell them, Away with the Chriſtians to the wilde beaſts; their motes be beams, their mole-hils moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, their flies be Eagles: and yet all <hi>England</hi> knows that there is ſcarce one to ten of your inſolent humour, who may not as eaſily be known from a ſober-minded Chriſtian, as a ſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering Morrice-dancer from an ordinary ſpectator, by his phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtick habit and behaviour.</p>
            <p>In the ſame <hi>p.</hi> 13. <hi>I have heard Papiſts ſay,</hi> &amp;c. And I have heard Papiſts upbraiding us with diſſention, not for any mans being divided from himſelf, but ſome of us from others by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariety of opinion: and how well ſoever you agree with your ſelf, you are not the leaſt fomenter of that diviſion.</p>
            <p>What <hi>p.</hi> 14. you declaim againſt peoples taking Religion up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on truſt, is worthy acknowledgement, and not unfrequently do we hear from this Clergy, which you look ſo deſpitefully on, the ſame doctrine. Many time have I heard them exhort to imitation of the <hi>Bereans,</hi> and preſt that precept of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.39. <hi>Search the Scriptures;</hi> that ſo they might at length tell the Church, as the <hi>Samaritans</hi> did the woman, <hi>Now we beleeve, not becauſe of thy word,</hi> &amp;c. that ſo if a new Religion come in faſhion, and the ſtream of the times turn, they may
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49844:11"/>have bank to hold by, ground of their own to ſtand on, and not be carried away with every blaſt of vain doctrine. But if conſtancy in perillous times, and ſtability in Religion ſignifie a ſure foundation, whether ſhall your fickleneſs or other mens perſeverance moſt commend them to the Church of God? For, you ſay, you were ſometime of the ſame minde, ſick, as you call it, of the ſame diſeaſe; and I wiſh for your everlaſting healths ſake you were Sermon-ſick in another ſenſe then you are. If your meaning be you were one of them that have no more but an implicit faith, I will yield you ſick of a dangerous diſeaſe indeed: but if you apply it to the condition of all them you write againſt, I think you may be anſwered as the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, who having read over the ſumme of Chriſtian Religion, and ſaying, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> was replied unto, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Or rather in the words of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>John,</hi> You went out from us becauſe you were not of us, if you had b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en of us, you would have continued with us.</p>
            <p>In <hi>p.</hi> 15. <hi>And therefore men cannot juſtly be taxed of immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty,</hi> &amp;c. To tax people of immodeſty for bare queſtioning, will not ſuit with the fore-mentioned doctrine: It is the duty of Miniſters to endeavour their doubting peoples reſolution: to many of whom I may apply for their commendation, what of <hi>Sempronia</hi> is recorded to her infamy, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t ſaepius peteret viros quam peteret.</hi> For I know them publiquely to incourage, and privately to invite men to this duty: and yet I muſt tell you that it's oftentimes ſeen that where duty may leade a man to make queſtion, there may be immodeſty uſed in manner of propounding and maintaining. Men that have not learned to deny themſelves, may pertinaciouſly perſiſt in an erroneous opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, to which ſelf-love hath ſo married that nothing but death can ſeparate them: Men many times defend their opinions as they do their Countries, not becauſe true, but becauſe their own. And I am perſwaded that not only many a baſtard-Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, but ſome even of the truly regenerated, are of ſuch pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh and croſs-grained diſpoſition, that an Angel from heaven could ſcarce give them ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>What clue was woond up in your diſcourſe, <hi>p.</hi> 16, 17, 18, 19, 20. is by your ſelf unravel'd again <hi>p.</hi> 21. for by producing ſome texts of Scripture ſounding free-grace, and ſome free-will, you
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49844:11"/>endeavour to evince, what before you have aſſerted concerning contradictions in Religion, as our Pulpit-men exhibit it. But in <hi>p.</hi> 21. you confeſs <hi>Can</hi> and <hi>Cannot</hi> in a divers reſpect may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſist well enough, as 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Not that we are ſufficient of our ſelves to think any thing as of our ſelves, but all our ſufficiency is of God.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. For God doth not <hi>nolentes vi trahere,</hi> and draw men to heaven as <hi>Cacus</hi> drew beaſts into his den, backward, but by a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> makes them willing: and God by his word com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding what we muſt do, gives us power to do what he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth. But if you ſay, this is not ſufficiently diſtinguiſht in teaching, I anſwer that you do not conſider how the ſame ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject ſhould be differently handled by a Rhetorician and a bare Logician: If Preachers ſhould uſe in their publique Sermons nothing but definitions and diviſions, what impreſs were they like to make on the peoples affections? And yet in regard to peoples infirmity, I could wiſh that Goſpel-truths were by ſome men, at ſome times held out more diſtinctly then they are. But he that is acquainted with the body of Divinity need not alwaies be poring on a Skeleton, but uſing an ingenuous can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor in hearing, he can diſcern the joints and nerves of diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Aporiſms thereto belonging, under the fleſh and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ornaments of amplification.</p>
            <p>And what is ſaid to this may likewiſe be applied to <hi>p.</hi> 22. where you would ſeem to make contradictory things in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſubordinate; <hi>viz.</hi> Gods election, and mans accepting the means of ſalvation; for God hath ordained to the end by the means. So alſo concerning the perſeverance of the faithfull and their ſeeming poſſibility of falling (for I may not be allowed here to ſtate the queſtions, it is done largely enough already by others.) In all which allegations you tranſlate the preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded crime from the Miniſters to the Scriptures; for whatſoever oppoſitions you gather out of their Sermons are either the ſame <hi>totidem verbis,</hi> or at moſt but a Paraphraſe on the holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures.</p>
            <p>To your rule <hi>p.</hi> 23. I give my approbation, and the rather, not becauſe new, but for that it's common: <hi>Bonum quo communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, eo melius.</hi> For as without uſe of the common elements no man can continue is his being; ſo neither without this rule
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49844:12"/>did any man ever reade the Scriptures with underſtanding. It is much therefore that you ſhould deigne to inſert it in this your ſupercilious inſultation. I have known many ſelf-conceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Scioli</hi> indeed who thought they told news when they did but carry herbs to <hi>Ephrata;</hi> (as the Jewiſh Proverb hath it) And although it be very little that I know in compariſon to what I ought, yet I have ſcarce had patience enough ſometimes in hearing ſuch punies documentizing me in obvious things; which becauſe new to them, they thought had been ſo to me, although I had known them from my childehood as familiarly as mine own name. But becauſe we erre not ſo much by igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance as incogitancy, I will ſuppoſe that you have given us this inſtruction for the help of our memory rather then of our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; but on this condition, that you will from hence take occaſion of conſidering, what neceſſary uſe we have of a conſtant Miniſtry; for although men know as much or more then the Preacher can tell them, yet have they ſtill great need of hearing. He that is of God (as well <hi>in facto,</hi> as <hi>in fieri)</hi> hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Gods Word; which is the means of growing as well as of begetting, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2. And as the body hath ſtill need of nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment, although it be come to its full <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which it will have ſupplied by a ſlovenly Cook, rather then periſh with famine: So the ſoul even of a ſtrong-grown Chriſtian is not kept by the power of God unto ſalvation otherwiſe, then by his Ordinances (where they are exhibited) of Sacraments and Preaching. We know in generall <hi>Publicorum cura est mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor,</hi> and if there be not men enough appointed for that ſacred imploiment, it is like to be but badly performed. Many an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate Maſter hath a gratious ſervant, many an irreligious parent a pious childe by Gods bleſſing on the publique Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, who had had ſmall means of enlightning otherwiſe: And ſince the rains of Government have lien but looſely on the peoples neck, how many Churches ſtand like deſerted Abbies appointed to demolition? We thought much in time of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops to have had no other afternoons exerciſe in ſome places, but Praier and Catechiſing: but many Pariſhes have now, nor one nor other: They who can procure means will not, they who would cannot, and ſo in concluſion,
<q>Et ſuccus pecori, &amp; lac ſubducitur agnis.</q>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:49844:12"/>Beſides, it is to be conſidered that although things abſolutely neceſſary to be beleeved are but few, yet there are many things to be done: the greater part by far of the word of God, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains direction for a godly converſation. For although Love be the fulfilling of the Law, yet this Charity hath ſo many ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and (by reaſon of corruption from within, and temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation from without) ſo many impediments, that it requires many rules of direction, and of them, becauſe of our many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, a frequent inculcation. But what need other reaſons? we are ſure it's Gods command, and therefore muſt needs be our duty. 'Twas not the ineſtimableneſs of the fruit, but the Infiniteneſs of the Prohibitant, that gave hainouſneſs to the ſin of <hi>Adam:</hi> nor are the Ordinances of God neceſſary for the efficacie of the outward Action, but in regard to the authority of Divine inſtitution. <hi>It pleaſeth God by the fooliſhneſs of preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſave them that believe,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.21. while to others it is ſaid, <hi>Behold ye deſpiſers, wonder and periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>p.</hi> 20. you tell us, that <hi>for ſolution of queſtions in Religion you have ſomewhat more to ſay then ever you heard or read from theſe men.</hi> Now if you have a better key to open the Scriptures with then other men, how dare you be ſo injurious to the Church of God as to conceal it? ſeeing, <hi>Qui novit, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> id quod ſentit exprineit, perinde eſt ac ſi neſciret.</hi> And if it be one of the things which people cannot yet bear (for ſuch things you ſpeak of, <hi>p.</hi> 5, 6.) how unjuſtly do you blame the Clergy for not lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch an unſupportable burden on them? What you know more then others, is to others unknown, but I am ſure know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge unſanctified is but like a ſword in a mad mans hand, and many a mans learning may be to himſelf but a candle to light him to hell. <hi>Multos naſci, &amp; omni ſcientia egere ſatius fuiſſet, quam ſic in propriam perniciem inſanire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>p.</hi> 24. you tell us of our neareſs to the Papiſts: in expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions I ſuppoſe you mean, which are moſt expanſe; for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the world knows we are at ſufficient diſtance. But concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this my opinion is, that we have gone farther from the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts then we need in ſome things, although not ſo far as they have gone from the truth in other.</p>
            <p>For reſolution to your inſtance, <hi>p.</hi> 25. <hi>[They ſay that a man hath power to do good works, but we ſay he hath not.]</hi> I anſwer,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49844:13"/>that Although it be God that worketh in us to will and to do of his own good pleaſure: and every Chriſtian may truly ſay of his graces, and all operations from them proceeding, as <hi>Jacob</hi> of his children, They are <hi>they which God hath graciouſly given to his ſervant;</hi> yet <hi>THE REGENERATED MAN IS IN A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLED BY THE GRACE OF GOD ASSISTING HIM, TO DO GOD MORE AND BETTER SERVICE THEN THAT WHICH HE DOTH.</hi> Which Propoſition well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered may much extricate a minde infetterd with ſeeming op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of this nature: And the ſame refutes that groſs ſpeech of your [<hi>When we are humbled for our ſins we do tell God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty news, that he would have had us walk more holily then we have done, but we had not power ſo to walk.</hi> And what you there ſpeak of faiths being a work, we muſt underſtand of the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere,</hi> for otherwiſe it is not true: But who of our Preachers ever ſaid that faith was a meritorious cauſe of ſalvation, and did not rather acknowledge the very <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to be from Chriſt? and if ſo, they affirm no more of faith then they do of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as to this particular.</p>
            <p>But <hi>p.</hi> 26. The Papiſts ſay good works are meritorious, but we ſay No, and yet I have heard it ſaid, if we believe, repent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it is Gods duty to give us heaven. The word Duty ſeems ſomewhat too harſh: but ſith we cannot underſtand Gods acting toward us, but according to the ſlender model of our apprehenſion, we may with due reverence to his glorious Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty affirm; That although our works do not by any merit in them, oblige God to reward them: yet we having his promiſe for our aſſurance, are as truly aſcertained of the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof, as if God were Debtor and we Creditors. The ſumme whereof is, That the true Beleever hath the Juſtice as well as the Mercy of God for his <hi>Aſylum,</hi> and may pray with the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Deliver me in thy righteouſneſſe.</hi> For Chriſt having ſatisfied the Juſtice of God for him, and imputed his own Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs to him, he may expect from God that fruition of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, which Chriſt hath purchaſed for him; of which the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent grace of God inabling him to beleeve, and endeavour to obey, gives teſtimony. For they do not ſay that Gods reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men is <hi>aequalitatis,</hi> but <hi>liberalitatis,</hi> not <hi>condignitatis,</hi> but <hi>benignitatis;</hi> and that he rewardeth not <hi>propter,</hi> but <hi>ſecundùm
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49844:13"/>opera:</hi> which very <hi>ſecundùm,</hi> as I underſtand it, ſignifies but this, To whom God gives greater meaſures of grace here, on them he will beſtow greater degrees of glory hereafter: not in regard of eſſential happines, which muſt be equal to all, but in reſpect of accidental bleſſedneſs, making ſuch a difference as is between the members of the body, although every member be equally informed by the ſame ſoul, and hath in it ſelf whatſoever can make for its perfection. In <hi>p.</hi> 28. you confeſs your whole diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to be negative: which choice whether it were made for your eaſe or not, you may thereby take to your ſelf the greater liberty of accuſing, and whatever anſwer be given, you can ſcarce be deſtitute of ſome means of evaſion.</p>
            <p>After that you invade the title <hi>Ambaſſadours of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> as owned by the Clergy. I wiſh you would (if ſuch a thing can be done) but pen ſome diſcourſe bare of Tropes and Figures, every word ſignifying according to its natural propriety, and then ſee what a deformed piece of work it will be: no doubt but a knife from off the Anvil will be near as uſefull, and what rules of art or reaſon can require ſuch ſeverity of expreſſion? But that I may play with you a little at your own game, what do you diſlike it for? You ſay, <hi>They underſtand not their Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage.</hi> In a ſecular ſignification, you may know better then I, what belongs to that Office: but if <hi>Legatus</hi> be an Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, and it be the eſſential form that denominates, then is it the being ſent, and not the manner of negotiation that makes an Ambaſſadour: He that carries the Ambaſſie muſt be the Ambaſſadour, whether tranſported by word or writing: if not, what means <hi>Hypſipyle</hi> ſaying of her new-born children,
<q>Legatos quos pene dedi pro matre ferendos?</q> And yet how can they be ſaid ignorant of that meſſage, which is ſo effectually done that multitudes of ſouls to their everlaſting comfort, have received the glad tidings of ſalvation by them delivered? And if you pleaſe to view the term in Greek, the ſame word which the Apoſtle uſeth, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.26. tranſlated, <hi>We are his Ambaſſadours,</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which muſt needs be neer of kin to <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, being both derived from the ſame <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Which title the bleſſed Apoſtle doth not arrogate to himſelf, but ſpeaks in the firſt perſon plural, as if he ſhould ſay, <hi>We,</hi> whether <hi>Paul</hi> or <hi>Apollos</hi> or <hi>Cephas,</hi> or what Miniſter ſoever
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49844:14"/>elſe by whom men beleeved. And the ſame Apoſtle <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.14. commendeth the <hi>Galatians</hi> for receiving him, not only as the Embaſſadour of Jeſus Chriſt, but as Chriſt himſelf: now between whether (think you) was the great diſparity, Chriſt and <hi>Paul,</hi> or <hi>Paul</hi> and Presbyters? Surely if it were commendable in them to receive <hi>Paul</hi> as Chriſt, it cannot be blameable in us to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them as <hi>Paul.</hi> What, would you have none allowed for preachers of the Word untill they be called, as that Apoſtle was, immediatly from Heaven? when Chriſt had called <hi>Andrew,</hi> he called <hi>Peter,</hi> when Chriſt had called <hi>Philip,</hi> he called <hi>Natha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neel;</hi> and ſo when the Apoſtles and Diſciples of our Saviour were ſent to preach the Goſpel themſelves, they alſo called others to the ſame, in effect, function. And I know not why we may not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the ſame ſucceſſion ſtill, unleſſe the whole Church of God can ratifie nothing without your approbation. If the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall call be queſtioned, he or none that pretends to the calling, muſt reſolve it; for I hope you have no more of the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> then they that lay on hands in ordination. It is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for us that the efficacy of divine miniſtration depends not of the ſanctity of the perſon miniſtring; or elſe <hi>Judas</hi> had never been an Apoſtle; for he was one of them whom Chriſt ſent to preach; witneſſe his appellation <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Nor have diſcerned any ſo great indignity caſt upon Gods Ordinances by the religious people of my time, as that Idolizing of Miniſters, and making Gods Word mans, while they profeſſedly hear it with respect of perſons.</p>
            <p>In <hi>p.</hi> 29. You endeavour to make void that title, as to them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing, becauſe <hi>they depend on the Civill Magiſtrates autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in their acting. As the Aſſembly of Divines waited on the Parliament with their Creed and Catechiſm.</hi> And would not the Apoſtles themſelves, if there had been Chriſtian Magiſtrates in their time, have implored their aſſiſtance for the furthering of their proceedings? <hi>I, but they ask leave of men to do what their Master hath commanded them.</hi> I anſwer, in our duty to God ſome things are eſſentiall, ſome accidentall: for the firſt we need no mans leave, the command of God lays on us a neceſſity of performance: but for other circumſtances thereto belonging, we may, yea and ought to be regulated by Magiſtrates. Beſides, the Aſſembly convened by authority of Parliament, and therefore whatever the members thereof act other wiſe in reference to their
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49844:14"/>miniſteriall office, yet <hi>quatenus</hi> Synod-men, they depend of the Parliament that call'd and upheld them. But your words ſeem to import a reſtraint by the Parliament laid upon them: and if ſo, it no more derogates from the truth and dignity of their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſteriall function to be ſo impedited by any outward obſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then it did from the bleſſed Apoſtle <hi>Pauls,</hi> whoſe viſitation of the Church of <hi>Theſſolonica</hi> was once or twice hindred by Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.18.</p>
            <p>In <hi>pag.</hi> 33. you promiſe us a <hi>pregnant Argument, that such men are not ſent by Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> that is, <hi>their difference in judgement.</hi> 'Twas well you did not ſay <hi>impregnable;</hi> for I hope your mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing being underſtood, we ſhall eaſily diſprove your argument. For do you affirm them to differ in the Fundamentals, or in the ſuperſtruction of religion? If the firſt, we deny your aſſertion. For which of them oppoſeth <hi>Peters</hi> enunciation, on which Chriſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to build his Church, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.18. we beleeve and are ſure that thou art Chriſt the Son of the living God? who among them confeſſeth not the holy Trinity, the Divinity and Humanity of our Saviour, his obedience and ſatisfaction, the Souls immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, laſt Judgement and life eternall? but if their difference be in non-neceſſaries, we have no where promiſe of infallibility in ſuch particulars; I hope Saint <hi>Paul</hi> had immediate aſſiſtance, and yet his (though but conditionall) toleration to the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> doth not <hi>omnimodò quadrare</hi> with that decree made by the Apoſtles and Elders at <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> What ſhall I ſpeak of that diſaſtrous claſhing between the Maſter-builders at <hi>Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chia?</hi> Act. 15.37, 38. or of <hi>Pauls</hi> ſevere reprehenſion of S. <hi>Peter</hi> for his double-dealing between the Jew and the Gentile? what diviſions are there amongſt ours more then about the fringe of Chriſts garment, and ſuch as were it not for other mens intereſt more then the Clergies, might probably in good part be well com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed. What is there more plainly then the abolition of Jewiſh ceremonies taught in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> doctrine? and yet it's affirmed that 15. Chriſtian Biſhops ſucceſſively were circumciſed in <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> before its deſtruction: and if it might be ſuppoſed that ſome of ours were for, and ſome againſt Paedobaptiſm, it will be no greater blemiſh then rebaptization was to <hi>Cyprian.</hi> Unity in doctrine and manners is indeed deſireable, but perfect harmony is reſerved for the life to come, of which there can be here but
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49844:15"/>an imperfect inchoation: God who bringeth good out of evill makes his Miniſters infirmities, like <hi>Pauls</hi> bonds, fall out many times for the furtherance of the Goſpel. Their contention in the forementioned Text was very high <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> even like the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſharpneſſe of feaver fit: for although they were Apoſtles yet they were men, —<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for God by their ſeparation made way to the further ſpreading of the Goſpel. No wonder therefore the Apoſtle ſaith there muſt be <hi>hereſies even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst you,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.19. And yet further to convince you of the inſufficiency of your argument, do but conſider whether the men whom you approve (if any you do allow) for Miniſters of the Word, be not men ſubject to like infirmities with theſe you ſpeak againſt; and if ſo, what validity hath your argument a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt one more then againſt the other?</p>
            <p>In <hi>p.</hi> 34. You compare <hi>Gods praying people to Fools and Knaves in Stage-plays, and that for their wry mouths, ſquint eyes, and ſcru'd faces.</hi> I beleeve they are not more like a Player for action, then you a Poet for expreſſion, or elſe you have learned what that <hi>Syren Attica</hi> gave for a deſcriprion of Oratory, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. But they are not (you ſay) the men that God and nature made them. Why? God made man to look upwards:
<q>
                  <l>Os homini ſublime dedit, coelumque tueri</l>
                  <l>Juſſit, &amp; erectos ad ſyderatollere vultus.</l>
               </q> and yet are men ſquint-eyed for looking up to heaven-ward? no nor for looking downards neither; for who diſallows the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans humble deportment? God hath made man to go upright on his feet, and yet never blames him for kneeling, or falling flat on his face in divine worſhip. Surely it would better argue a gracious heart, not raſhly to cenſure any good endeavour, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it were accompanied with ſome ſmall indiſcretion in the actor. But you ſay you are aſſured that if the exacteſt ſcrutiny be made, there can be no precept or example found for it. But as confident as you are, you forgat <hi>Hanna,</hi> 1 Sam. 1.13. which, but for her trembling lips and blubred face, could not in her very prayer have been taken for a drunken woman. Whether you have like fervency of ſpirit in prayer or no, I cannot hope that you would uſe like mildeneſſe of ſpeech, had you lain under a like cauſeleſſe reprehenſion. Our Lord forbids diſguiſing faces in hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49844:15"/>
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.16. but why was any ſuch thing done in hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, if it had not a character of good affection when done in ſincerity; for the hypocrites counterfeited a ſorrowfull counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, that they might gain to themſelves the opinion of devout men by that outward imitation. The face naturally characteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeth the minde; and when <hi>frons eſt animi mutabilis index,</hi> the the diſparity is made <hi>de industria.</hi> and of ſet purpoſe: and that not only in the height of an affection, for we many times gueſſe rightly by a ſtrangers countenance at what good will he bears to the profeſſion of Religion, <hi>Momus</hi> might have been ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned to Natures Court, for ſaying mans body wanted win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows in the breaſt, for a mans countenance, garments and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture do bewray his diſpoſition, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 19.27, 28. But I marvail how any man whoſe face is as though he would go to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> can thut deride the diſcoveries of the Spirit of God, his ſtriving within men. My heart is extreamly hard (the Lord in mercy mollifie it) and yet I could not utter theſe words as you ſpeak them, and not tremble in rehearſing. Artificial modulation of the voice of which you ſpeak, <hi>p.</hi> 35. is, no doubt to be rectified by Chriſtian prudence, for every art is but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and all things in the Church muſt be done to edification. But ſeeing you affirm it to be done in hypocriſie, I can have but heavy thoughts of you while I meaſure your faith by your charity.</p>
            <p>In <hi>p.</hi> 36. you promiſe clearly to demonſtrate our Clergies ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities and groſſeneſſe by ſinging Pſalms: but upon examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion you are ſo far from a ſcientificall, that you have not ſo much as a probable argument; for if any man irrationally abuſe the Pſalms, is this an abſurdity in the Clergy, and that the whole Clergy? as if <hi>quatenus</hi> Clergy they were all irrational in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular. I hope it will not make a little for their vindication, that you are ſo hardly driven to finde ſomewhat againſt them, that you muſt needs forge this falſe accuſation. I know the contrary practiſed by many Miniſters in publike exerciſes, and by all reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious perſons that I have known to ſing Pſalms in their private houſes. To take Pſalms at a venture, or to go through the whole Book in order, doth indeed ſeem to me abſurd and irrationall: but to ſelect one or two ſtaves, or more, ſuteable to their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and to reade it themſelves, is the common practice of many godly Miniſters, and I have known Pariſh-Clarks ſo to demean
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49844:16"/>themſelves in that office, that they deſerved commendation of all their Auditors: and that it may with heed-taking in the choice of a Pſalm, and ſometimes by change of a word, be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed; I have moſt part of my time known by experience. That is not true (which you would perſwade us) that not one Pſalm of the 150. can indifferently be ſung by a whole Congregation; for to ſay nothing of the Jews great Halelujah ſung at their Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, and moſt probably by our Saviour and his company, from 113. Pſalm to the 119. excluſively, it is contrary to the experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of all well conſiderate Chriſtians. For daily exerciſe indeed, and to ſave people a labour in chooſing, I have known ſelected parcels of Pſalms framed together, which were ſo compoſed by Godly Miniſters before I was born, and ſome copies of that kinde I have ſtill by me. So that to impute this abſurdity to the whole Clergy is as unjuſt as that of the profane multitude: Some Puritans are knaves, and ſo they are all: Some profeſſors are hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, and therefore all are no better: and I wonder a man that talks ſo much of rationality ſhould bring in this for a demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration.</p>
            <p>I cannot cloſe with you in <hi>p.</hi> 38. neither where you ſay, <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the people are undeſervedly cenſured for withdrawing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from ſuch meetings.</hi> That becauſe they cannot at ſome times joyn in ſome one exerciſe, they ſhould caſt off all: eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſidering how eaſily ſuch an irregularity might be correct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and that indeed you would rather have endeavoured, if ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion more then reformation were not the ſcope of your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention.</p>
            <p>In the ſame Page you make <hi>the Clergy the main Incendiaries in stirring up people againſt the Parliament:</hi> and this too muſt be ſet upon the common head, as the fault of the whole Clergy; whereas all the Chriſtian world knows, had it not been for what influence the Clergy had upon the people, there had long ere this time been no Parliament to be oppoſed.</p>
            <p>In <hi>pag.</hi> 40. You upbraid the Clergy with being beholden to a <hi>Lexicons</hi> and you might as well have ſaid a Horn-book or Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar, for to them they may have been beholden too: what diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement is it for the higheſt building to have had its foundation low in the earth? or if you mean the conſtant uſe of it, no mans memory is infinite. <hi>We know but in part, and propheſie but in part,</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:49844:16"/>1 Cor. 13 8, 10, 11. And yet for all this (you ſay) ſome of them have ſuch bold foreheads, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> more skill then the Septuagint. Sir, it being acknowledged by the Church, that the 70. were not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, I know not why a modeſt man having more then 70. times 70. of his judgement, may not as well cleave to theſe as to them, their tranſlation as well as others being ſubject to diſquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And what if a Miniſter, not ſo much as they Maſter of the Languages, meet with one of the errors of the Seventy, in which they did <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as is obſerved by the learned, is it ever the leſſe true in his mouth, becauſe he was not the firſt that diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered it?</p>
            <p>In <hi>p.</hi> 41. <hi>Becauſe they know many of the Lay-men are good Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, and better then many of them, &amp;c. they are in Orders for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth,</hi> &amp;c. Theſe words of yours are inconſiſtent with Piety and Polity: Firſt, They are againſt Piety; for never did any people, how barbarous ſoever, worſhip a God, who did not alſo acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge a Prieſt. And yet if the naturall Law had been quite extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, ſacred Orders are evidently grounded upon the Word of God, and have been with reverence admitted in all ages of the Church. It was not the leaſt circumſtance aggravating the ſin of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> that in his time, who would might conſecrate himself, and become Prieſt of the high places; and yet they were not ſo irreligious as to ſerve without ſome kinde of conſecration. To what hath been already ſaid to this purpoſe, I ſhall only adde here this one Text more. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.15. <hi>Who can preach except he beſent? dejure</hi> (I ſuppoſe) all men underſtand it, not <hi>de facto:</hi> and <hi>Origens</hi> many errors have in the judgement of the Church been imputed to his ſo long neglect of Orders. But they derive their title from the Biſhops, whom (you ſay) they will not own. That I may ſpeak my minde freely, I think that Presbyters in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king off Epiſcopall propts, did but as it were pull an old houſe on their head, and it would have made more for the good of the Church, if Epiſcopacy had ſtood with its due regulation. But ſo it comes to paſſe through the deceitfulneſſe of our hearts, that When Gods cauſe and our own concurre, we are apt <hi>Jehu</hi> like to drive furiouſly: and truly I think many of the Presbyters (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hom I deſervedly honour) as well as the people following their hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, have not been free of envy or coveteouſneſſe in proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that deſign, of which by this time it may have repented
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49844:17"/>them. But whether they acknowledge them for Biſhops or no, it is ſure they never diſallowed them as Miniſters, and what then will their receiving their call from them make to your pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe? M. <hi>Luther</hi> renounced his Monaſtick life, becauſe it was not allowed by the Word of God to vow what was not in the votiſts power: but he never renounced his Order although re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in the Popiſh manner: no more did any other of the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyred Biſhops and other Miniſters (as far as I remember) who deſerted the Romiſh Church as well as he. We miſtake the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> if we imagine it ſo full of errour as to have had no truth left in it: For certain it is not ſo much corrupted as were the 10. Tribes during the reign of 19. Kings ſucceſſively in <hi>Iſrael:</hi> and he that well obſerves the ſtate of the Jewiſh Church in the daies of our Saviour, will finde it ſcarce ſo good as the Romiſh Church now. But howſoever, if Orders be given and received now with us, according to that direction which the Apoſtles left, and the primitive Saints practiſed, what need we trouble our ſelves with any intermediats? <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaid <hi>Ignatius:</hi> and therefore, as to themſelves, they need not regard your horrid ſarcaſm, in theſe following words; By which impſition of hands the holy Ghoſt is conveyed into them, <hi>as it was brought out of Scotland in a Cloak-bag.</hi> And why is it not conferred? becauſe all ſuch gifts as ſome had in the Apoſtles time are not given; the ſecond temple of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> might then have been diſallowed, for that it wanted beſides magnitude and ſtatelineſſe of ſtructure, 1. The Ark of God. 2. The <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim</hi> and <hi>Thummim.</hi> 3. The glory of God appearing between the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubims. 4, The fire that deſcended from Heaven and conſumed the ſacrifices. 5. The immediate gift of prophecie: for from the daies of <hi>Malachi</hi> to <hi>John the Baptist,</hi> they had only what they call <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And yet the Prophet <hi>Hag.</hi> 2.9. ſaith the glory of the ſecond houſe ſhall exceed that of the firſt. But as the name of God is by you in theſe words abuſed, ſo all good men ought to be troubled: for the ſame expreſſion is recorded for a moſt blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Proverb in the Hiſtory of the Councell of <hi>Trent</hi> tranſlated out of Italian by Sir <hi>N. Brent,</hi> lib.6. pag, 497. Although I know not whether <hi>Hezekiah</hi>'s command concerning <hi>Rabſhakeh</hi> be not here obſervable, Anſwer him not. Now the Lord himſelf behold and judge who moſt abuſeth his holy Name, you or the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters:
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49844:17"/>for mine own part I have no more to ſay to it, but <hi>The Lord rebuke thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſecondly, This ſentence is inconſiſtent with good Polity; for what confuſion muſt needs be brought into a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth by means not being allowed the free uſe of their vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but that every man who ſuppoſeth himſelf able for another mans calling ſhall take his place from him? The <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>topians</hi> to avoid unneceſſary profeſſions, were every man to make his own cloathes: but the prudent States-man, who deviſed it, never dream'd of ſuch an ataxie as you would bring in, who make no complaint of the vaineſt ſuperfluity, and yet purpoſely oppoſe that which is the one thing neceſſary. But I ſhould wrong the cauſe in hand by being beholden to any lower proof then the voice of Gods Spirit (ſeeing you deny your ſelf to be an Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripturiſt.) What can be plainer then that of the Apoſtle? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.24. What calling any man is in, let him therein abide. Or that of <hi>Peter,</hi> where he reprehends, as worthy of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; that is, Exerciſers of juriſdiction in other mens Dioceſes, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.15. What if other men be as good Scholars, is it nothing but ſcholarſhip that makes a Miniſter? I cannot think but that other Jews might be as handſome But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers and Cooks, as the Levites, who yet might not be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to kill and dreſſe their own ſacrifices. 'Tis true, Chriſt, though he called <hi>Levi,</hi> call'd no Levite, that he might aboliſh the former manner of worſhip: yet he choſe ſome to wait on this Miniſtry as they did on that, and of them diſtinct orders, as twelve Apoſtles, and ſeventy two Diſciples; and after his Aſcenſion, others by mediation of the Apoſtles; who are alſo ſaid to be ordained by the holy Ghoſt, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.28, either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Apoſtles were by the holy Ghoſt directed to that Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination of Miniſters where they had planted Churches, or becauſe the gifts of the Spirit inabling for that Office were in their laying on of hands conferred; or it may be for both. But that Chriſt appointed theſe orders in his Church, we may ſee, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And he would not have directed his Epiſtles by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>John</hi> in the ſecond and third Chapters of the <hi>Revelation</hi> to the Angels, that is, the Miniſters of the ſeven Churches, if he had not approved of that Office: And that it is with dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49844:18"/>to be proceeded in, the word is plain, <hi>He that hath an office let him wait on his office, he that teacheth on teaching, he that exhorteth on exhortation.</hi> Do but make the cauſe your own by ſuppoſing, if it could be proved that another man can husband your eſtate better then your ſelf, muſt he deprive you of your propriety? If another man be found more worthy to ſerve the ſtate then your ſelf, muſt he take from you that place to which you ſay you were choſen.</p>
            <p>In <hi>p.</hi> 42. you have yet another fling at them, and that is for <hi>waving queſtions when they cannot reſolve them:</hi> And this alſo, if it be true, is but a perſonall infirmity, and no whit impug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the Office of the Miniſtry. <hi>Tiſhbi ſolvet nodos,</hi> had not been a Proverb among the Jews, if they had not in ſome que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions of Religion been ſtill unreſolved. But if becauſe one Lawyer could not reſolve me in one Law-caſe, I ſhould call the Law an impoſture, and the Lawyers Juglers; would you not think me more fit for Bedlam then for any civil ſociety? and yet this were orthodox in your divinity. Concerning the oppoſition you would make between faith and reaſon (becauſe you both uſe, and require your Reſpondent to uſe all poſſible brevity,) I refer you for ſatisfaction to a little Book lately ſet forth, and intituled, <hi>The reaſonableneſſe of Chriſtian Religion.</hi> And what you ſay of the man of <hi>Macedonia</hi> (meaning a better living) and of the abuſe of Funeral Sermons, <hi>p.</hi> 44. is alſo to be reckoned among perſonall offences, which no man doth as a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, but as a ſinner, it being common to all men in ſome kinde or other to tranſgreſs.</p>
            <p>In <hi>p.</hi> 44. you have, <hi>While they are under ſuch diſpenſations they are in a Labyrinth of trouble, one while having reſt in their ſpirits, another while diſtraction, judging of the love and anger of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward them, according to their actings, as if God were as inconſtant as they.</hi> You would not be thought an Antiſcripturiſt, <hi>p.</hi> 51. You would not be thought to take men off from duty, <hi>p.</hi> 56. and yet you condemn that diſpenſation men are under, who are inconſtant in their feelings. Now whether are you in ſtate of Grace or Glory? this I hope you will not ſay, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will confute your opinion. I know Grace to be Glory in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choate, and Glory to be Grace conſummate: But by ſtate of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49844:18"/>Grace we underſtand that condition to Godward a man is in after his converſion, ſo long as corruption is inmate with grace, and like the <hi>Canaanites</hi> to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> will dwell with him: for ſin doth remain though it do not reign in the Regenerate, and grace is given to ſuſtain the ſoul againſt corruption and temptation: the filth continueth, though the guilt be removed, and the guilt, though wholly <hi>in foro divino,</hi> yet not ſo <hi>in foro conſcientiae,</hi> if whereſoever there be faith there is alſo infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: Faith is therefore call'd a ſhield, becauſe it defendeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt deſpair: Now no man can ſay his charity is perfect, or his patience undiſturbed, and yet muſt we beleeve any mans faith to be inſuperable, in evidence as well as adherence, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect as well as direct action? God give me faith ſo long as I have doubt, and when I ſhall have no longer doubt, I ſhall have no need of faith.</p>
            <p>But <hi>They judge of Gods love or anger,</hi> &amp;c. There is not any knowing Chriſtian that thinks love or anger to be in God, <hi>quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad affectum,</hi> becauſe it would argue mutability, which Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture and reaſon teach us cannot be in him: But <hi>quoad effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum</hi> we ought to judge; for the moſt faithfull ſervants of God upon their uneven walking, I mean their not ſticking ſo cloſe to the rules of obedience as ſometimes they do, and even when they do not, are inabled to do, obſerve, not only outward ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities, but inward deſertions ingruing: And whether God be diſpleaſed or no, ſurely every true childe of God will finde cauſe to be diſpleaſed with himſelf for his own diſobedience: And if any man that hat Gods Word for his guide, live under any higher diſpenſation, I acknowledge my ſelf to be experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally ignorant of that condition. And what is your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of this? You write only negatively, and ſo keep your ſelf in a cloud ſtill: But when you have ſublimed your conceptions of God, and extracted from them the pureſt quinteſſence, yet ſtill you have of him no adequate, but an analogical concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on only. God dwelleth in light inacceſſible: we can but <hi>per tranſennas videre,</hi> while we dwell in houſes of clay; and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee him as he is, while we have about us the body of ſin: Nor afterward neither can God be apprehended, more then <hi>ad modum apprehendentis.</hi> As therefore our Saviour ſaid in the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49844:19"/>Goſpel, Why trouble you the woman, for ſhee hath wrought a good work upon me? ſo, Why diſturb you the Church of God, putting people out of their good way, and obſcuring the light by which they walk, ſith you cannot hold them out a better? it is a greater light muſt overcome the leſſe; and when the Sun of Righteouſneſſe ſhall ariſe, the Moon and Starres may fail: but neither the Glow-worms of earthly preferment, nor the <hi>ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis lambens</hi> of flattering ſpeeches, nor the <hi>ignis fatuus</hi> of fanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick opinions ought to ſeduce us: no, nor the blazing comets of pretended revelations attract our confidence.</p>
            <p>An approver of which dotages you ſeem to be, <hi>p.</hi> 47. where you have theſe words, <hi>I am much ſatisfied in my ſpirit, having done that which I was convinced was my duty, by the stirrings within me to this thing for at leaſt a year paſt.</hi> But how came you to be convinced that you ought to revile them whom God commands you to honour? You ſay, <hi>by the ſtirrings within you:</hi> But what if the ſpirit within you luſteth to envy? we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to <hi>try the ſpirits whether they be of God or no,</hi> 1 Joh. 4.1. Now if your word be conſonant to the voice of Gods ſpirit in the holy Scriptures, God forbid, but that I ſhould lay my hand upon my mouth: but your drift is to undo the Clergy, which conſequently muſt deprive us of the means of ſalvation, which God by the men of that calling holds forth to us, and that upon no other ground then ſome of your own carps and crotchets, and contradictions, which you would have faſtned to their diſcourſes, but were fain to let them fall (rather then have them no where) upon the ſacred Scriptures. Set all the faults you have reckoned upon the tenters to make them odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and ſtretch them n longer then they will hold to be theirs, and they will be found but a few perſonall infirmities, ſuch as we cannot have men without, and ſuch as any but a Malignant <hi>Ham</hi> would rather cover then blazon abroad. You complain indeed of formality in religion, <hi>p.</hi> 44. and abuſe of Ordinances, <hi>p.</hi> 46. but how you knit theſe into the net you make to catch Clarks, in I ſee not. Irregularity in ſinging Pſalms hath the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt cauſe of complaint that I finde in your Book, and that's farre from being a property of the Clergy; for it agrees neither <hi>omni, ſoli</hi> nor <hi>ſemper,</hi> as is ſhewn before. The Word of God in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:49844:19"/>
               <hi>Pauls</hi> time was preached by ſome out of envy, by ſome out of vain-glory, by ſome out of covetouſneſſe, yet herein the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle rejoyced that it was at all preached, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.18. and if you had the ſame Spirit with Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> you would not ſhew your ſelf of a contrary mide. Sir, as you love your ſoul, take heed of truſting to your inward ſtirrings: You may be ſure the ſubtle Tempter will not ordinarily ſuggeſt to a religious man a temptation to open prophaneneſſe, becauſe it is not like to finde acceptance: but he will put into ſuch a mans head good thoughts ſometimes to keep out better, he will ſtrive to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe his hatred of meritorious conceits, thereby to inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate into him neglect of duty, and poſſeſſe him with grand deteſtation of formality in Religion, in hope thereby to beget in him a diſeſteem of Ordinances. Be not raſhly confident of ſuch motions, knowing that the devill in form of an Angel of light, may eaſily through the treachery of our deceitfull hearts inſnare us. I deſire to preſſe this conſideration the more earneſtly, becauſe the main of your diſcourſe conſiſts in accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, a practice from which the very devil takes his denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, as if it were the worſt quality he hath, or his very profeſſion; for ſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>dicitur</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as we have the word uſed, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.1. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he was accuſed. I ſay again, be not deceived: the devill brought a colourable accuſation againſt <hi>Job,</hi> and there is little more in all that ſatyrical inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive of your, as you apply it to the Clergy.</p>
            <p>In <hi>p.</hi> 48. You <hi>would not have people hearken to them in matters of State.</hi> If you had ſaid no more, I ſhould have had nothing to ſay againſt you; why did you not take that for your theam: and yet ſeeing you ſpeak ſo much of the Clergies intereſt, I may take notice of yours in this particular: for had not Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters medled in matters of State when time was, you had ſcarce had any State-matters to meddle with now. But how ſhall ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of conſcience depending on matters of State be reſolved? ſuppoſe (which no doubt hath been ſomewhere done) a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter be enquired of concerning the lawfullneſſe of taking the late Engagement; if he do his office, he fals under your cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure for medling in a State matter, if he refuſe, he is condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for a Malignant: ſo that a Clergy-man conſiding or diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding cannot be innocent:
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49844:20"/>
               <q>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</q> 
               <hi>But they ſtir up people againſt the Parliament</hi> (you ſay,) which if they do, I hope the Parliament hath better arms then your pen to defend it. But what makes you ſo hot in the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? you, who if you be out deſerve not to come in and if you be in, deſerve to be outed? doubtleſſe the worſt ſpoak in the wheel cracks firſt. Though you worſhip no Images, you may be a Worſhipper of imaginations, and adore the ſpurious brats of your own brain, begotten in ſpirituall fornication: and then the two-edged ſword in the mouth of the Clergy muſt needs terrifie you, being to divide between you and your errors. It may be there would be no cauſe of complaining of their being againſt the Parliament, if you were out of it. Hatred againſt powerfull Preachers of the Word, hath ever been a ſymptome of an unſound heart: and if your inſide were turned outward, I doubt we might there reade ſomewhat like the words of angry <hi>Agamemnon;</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
               </q> or that of <hi>Ahab</hi> concerning <hi>Micaiah,</hi> I hate him, becauſe he never propheſieth good to me but evill; Miniſters being for no other cauſe your enemies, but becauſe they tell you the truth. Such were the complaints that the rebellious Jews made againſt <hi>Jeremy;</hi> he fell away to the <hi>Chaldeans,</hi> he weakened the hands of the men of warre, he ſought not the proſperity but the hurt of the people: no leſſe then High Treaſon in every Article. So they by the Apoſtles in the <hi>Acts?</hi> Theſe are the men that have turned all the world upſide down; The very foundations are out of frame, but what hath the righteous done? they ſtir up peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple againſt the Parliament? What the Clergy, the whole Clergy, and <hi>quatenus</hi> Clergy? ſo that their very calling is oppoſite to the power and priviledge of Parliament? then lay all their faults upon me, if that can be proved, and
<q>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num pro multis dabitur caput.—</q> Then to prove what I know not who denies, you produce a place of Scripture, <hi>viz.</hi> Rom. 13.1, 2. <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject,</hi> &amp;c. Which becauſe it is poſitively and directly, whereas the reſt of your diſcourſe (as your ſelf confeſſe) is negative, and your texts
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49844:20"/>of Scripture but obliquely introduced, I will ſee how theſe words as a proof will ſtand with your prohibition of humane learning. Suppoſe any conſpiring ſervant make this plea for himſelf: I am under command and muſt obey that power to which I am ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; for all power is of God. And by like proportion may every underling thus defend his guilt in any rebellion, unleſſe you tell him that by power is meant lawfull authority, and not every force. But while <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, may be tranſlated power as well as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, how can you be able without Greek to confute the Defendant? So if it be demanded concerning the laſt word <hi>(damnation)</hi> why it is here annext to the breach of the fifth Commandement, ſeeing ſins againſt firſt Table are in their ſeverall order and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree more hainous then they againſt the ſecond; or if it be askt, why the word is rendred <hi>Damnation,</hi> it being not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is rather <hi>judicium,</hi> what ſatisfaction by bare meditation of the word, and that in Engliſh, can be given?</p>
            <p>In <hi>p.</hi> 49. <hi>Where there are any endowed with the ſpirit of prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, that declare the truth as it is in Jeſus, and that their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations as the one hand do not pull down,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I love them,</hi> &amp;c. But your plaiſter is too narrow for the wound which your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer diſcourſe hath made, of which if you will not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, I ſhall ſpeak in vain: and if you will you need no other inſtructer then your own experience in this matter. But whether you be perſwaded or no, you muſt not think to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade us that none of the Clergy you ſo deſpightfully taunt at, are ſincere publiſhers of the will of God, and men whoſe lives are ſuteable to the doctrine which they preach. Great was the cruelty which <hi>Nahaſh</hi> the <hi>Ammonite</hi> would have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed on the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> by putting out the right eyes of all the men of <hi>Jabeſh,</hi> 1 Sam. 11.2. but you endeavour to put out the eyes of our underſtanding, which would be by ſo much the more dangerous, by how much our ſouls are better then our bodies. Am I deceived, or do I not know the Sun when I ſee it ſhine? Whence, I trow, is this confidence of yours? if you were Emperour of the world, yet your moſt impetuous puiſſance could not violate our reaſon: had you <hi>Neſtor's</hi> lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49844:21"/>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Or had a ſtream of Eloquence like <hi>Euripus,</hi> that carried ſhips under ſail againſt the winde, yet were it not poſſible for you ſo farre to force our underſtanding, as on your bare word, (and that no Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans neither) to make us take for uniform moſt irreconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>In <hi>p.</hi> 50. <hi>Or have renounced their admiſſion to the Miniſtry, as ſome have done upon very good grounds, I am fully ſatisfied,</hi> &amp;c. I would you were elſe: but how ſhall other men be ſatisfied in this: Firſt, That a Miniſter may on good ground renounce his admiſſion to the Miniſtry? Or ſecondly, how having renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced his calling he is ſtill a Miniſter? You ſay, (though falſly) <hi>the Clergy is Pope-like in delivering Doctrine; for they exhort peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to examine it by the Scriptures:</hi> but what you are like I know not; for the Pope would not offer to obtrude ſuch ſtuff as this to the Iriſh themſelves, the moſt credulouſly facil in Religion of all Catholikes; That the ſame man is a Miniſter and not a Miniſter, upon profeſſion of his own ſatisfaction, with out any further reaſon or diſtinction.</p>
            <p>You profeſſe <hi>great ſelf-deniall</hi> but in <hi>p.</hi> 47. and tell us, how you <hi>brake through all danger your reputation was in, deſpiſing what the men of the world ſay,</hi> &amp;c. and yet I cannot ſee but that you are as tenderly affected with your reputation as any man elſe; for you apologize for it here and there, inveigh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your Antagoniſt, and take ſuch revenge as words will give you: I, and here <hi>p.</hi> 51. (to which all the reſt is as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing) you appeal to God for your vindication: which no man that reverenceth the name of God would do in a matter ſo contemptible as you would make your reputation.
<q>
                  <l>Non Deus interſit, niſi dignus vindice nodus</l>
                  <l>Inciderit.—</l>
               </q> Whether or no you love fame, it appears by your words, that <hi>you hate infamy;</hi> and thereby are in <hi>Cicero</hi>'s judgement worthy reprehenſion. <hi>Multi contemnunt mundi ſtrepitum, reputant pro nihilo gloriam, ſed timent infamiam, offenſionem repulſam, volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem ſeveriſſimè contemnunt, in dolore ſunt molliores, gloriam negligunt, franguntur infamia.</hi> Although I think a good name to be a bleſſing of God, and therefore to be much reſpected, and carefully preſerved.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:49844:21"/>
            <p>In <hi>p.</hi> 53. <hi>I am non of thoſe that ſqueeze and grinde the people to enrich themſelves.</hi> By like then you confeſſe there be ſome that do ſo: and ſeeing in the ſubſequent Page, you promiſe your ſelf in <hi>your Sphear to act againſt all corruptions of Church and State,</hi> me think you ought to have told who theſe op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſors be. For people receiving this ill report from you, will be ready to think, If ſuch oppreſſors be Officers under the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, why (being known) are they ſuffered? if any among themſelves, yet there the <hi>major</hi> part can overpower the <hi>minor,</hi> but if ſuch a complaint ſtill continue, what a reverend opinion of the Parliament is this diſgracefull report like to beget in the heart of the people? and yet all this is done to advance your even-now (if we will believe you) deſpiſed reputation. And now whether are you or the Clergy greater adverſary to the Parliament? I have no accuſation againſt you, or any man elſe in ſuch matters; but this I boldly affirm (and to your everlaſting infamy be it ſpoken) that if you be no Caterpillar procuring a corporall, yet you are no better then a Locuſt of the Bottomleſſe pit, endeavouring to procure a ſpirituall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, ſuch as the Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> ſpeaks of, <hi>chap.</hi> 8. <hi>verſ.</hi> 11, 12. <hi>not of bread, nor thirſt of water, but of hearing the Word of the Lord: when they ſhall go fromſea,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In <hi>p.</hi> 54. <hi>Church-men, as they are by ſome called, but how wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily, judge you.</hi> I will do as you bid me, and judge, as much reaſon for a Miniſter to be called a Church-man, as for M. <hi>Fry</hi> to be called a Parliament-man: and that whether you take Church for the people of God, or for the place of publike worſhip. And why not? you muſt give me leave to gueſſe at your meaning, for you do not reveal it, Now becauſe I have heard ſome (beſides ſelf-conceited novices) affirm Steeple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houses to be abſurdly called Churches, I may ſuppoſe you of the ſame opinion, and upon that ſuppoſition to deny to Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers the name of Church-men. But the truth is the houses are more properly called Churches then the people. Indeed if you ask me what is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; I anſwer, it is in its largeſt acceptation any Aſſembly, as <hi>Act.</hi> 19.41. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for, he diſmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Aſſembly; but in Divinity it is uſed to ſignifie, A peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple called out from the reſt of the world by the preaching of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:49844:22"/>the Goſpel. But what ſimilitude of ſound is there between <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia</hi> and Church? This word <hi>Church</hi> therefore differing but by corruption of ſpeech from <hi>Kirk,</hi> is an abbreviate of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Lords Houſe.</hi> Now theſe places appointed for publick wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip are certainly houſes in proper ſpeech, whereas the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God are called a <hi>houſe</hi> metaphorically, in regard of their reſemblance to a materiall building: but we having not a word properly to denominate the people by, uſe this word <hi>Church,</hi> when applied to them by a Metonymie: as the Latines on the other ſide apply the word <hi>Eccleſia</hi> to the houſe, which properly ſignifies the people: to avoid (as I ſuppoſe) the Roman <hi>Templum</hi> as Heatheniſh, and the Greek <hi>Synagogue</hi> as Jewiſh. Whence it appears, that the houſes only are in proper ſpeech called Churches: to which every man elſe of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation belongeth but according to his generall calling of Chriſtianity, but the Miniſter alſo by his particular calling, from which men take their denomination: ſo we ſay, Wool-men, Silk-men, Heard-men, and why not (but that your envy can allow them nothing that is good) Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men?</p>
            <p>In <hi>p.</hi> 54. You expreſs <hi>your confidence in God, for being carried to the Land of Reſt:</hi> and that on this ground, as it ſeems to me, which is contained in the very next words, <hi>I having no miſgotten goods to ſtare in the face of my conſcience, nor errors, nor blaſphemies to affright me;</hi> and preſently after you confeſs <hi>your dependance on the love of God through his Son.</hi> Which words I no whit diſlike in themſelves; for I acknowledge works to juſtifie not only before men, but in the Court of conſcience, as they teſtifie the truth of our faith: from which office the infirmities that accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny them do no more derogate, then the imperfection of our faith from the truth of our beleeving. But ſeeing you are ſo curiouſly criticall againſt our Preachers for want of all poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble perſpicuity in every expreſſion, you may conſider how unkindely you would take it, on ſo ſlight occaſion to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed as guilty of a contradiction. For in theſe words you do not only allow in your ſelf what you condemn in others, <hi>p.</hi> 44. concerning <hi>inconſtancy of aſſurance according to inſtability of action in the duties of obedience;</hi> but you jumble Faith and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:49844:22"/>Works together, Sanctification (though but privative) and Juſtification by the merits of Chriſt: and if ſo ſtrong a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber as you would ſeem to be, have ſuch tender ears as to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of contradictions, or confuſe expreſſions, where other men apprehend no ſuch matter, it's poſſible ſome other upon this occaſion may make bold to taunt you in the words of the Satyriſt;</p>
            <q>Loripedem rectus derideat, Aethiopem albus.</q>
            <p>And now may I ſay of our Shepheards what <hi>David</hi> of his Metaphoricall ſheep, What have they done? Many good works have I done among you, ſaid our Saviour to the Jews, <hi>for which of them do you ſtone me?</hi> ſo many good things have we received from the Clergy, for which of them do you thus (to uſe <hi>C. Agrippa's</hi> phraſe) <hi>lapides loqui?</hi> Is it nothing to be excluded the Parliament as an inconſiderable part of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? nothing for them to abridge themselves in lawfull recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations, for fear of other mens exceſſe in imitation? nothing to be worried with unceſſant clamours of Schiſmaticks? and which is worſt of all, that the precious balms of Gods own peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple (by ill applying) ſhould break their heads, and cauſe them to pray alſo againſt their wickedneſſe? Is it for this they ſpend and are ſpent?</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Hunc fertilitatis honorem</l>
               <l>Officijque refers? —</l>
            </q>
            <p>Is this the reward of their Labour? Is it for this they ſtrain their wits, macerate their bodies, neglect proviſion for themſelvrs and poſterities, and contract remedileſſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes?
<q>Hoc eſt cur pallet, cur quis non prandeat hoc eſt?</q> Such diſcouragements to learning, if but for politique reaſons would be unſufferable. Well may Colledges be empty of Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, when mens mouths are full of reproaches, and their hands of injuries againſt that, which is the chiefeſt end of all their ſtudies. <hi>Invitatus ad haec aliquis de ponte, negabit.</hi> If other men were of your minde, how contemptible would this ſacred Function be? <hi>Praeſtaret dentiſcalpia radere, quam literarijs mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numentis inſudare.</hi> Reſpect and maintenance you would deprive them of, and what then will they have left that men can take
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:49844:23"/>from them? It is well their mental endowments are without the reach of your ſacrilegious clutches, or elſe they had been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured too: unleſſe you would forbear (as <hi>Tiberius</hi> refuſed to take the life of one whom he was minded to torment) that by them they may be the more apprehenſive of their miſery. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitors on thoſe words of <hi>Job</hi> 19.20. <hi>I have eſcaped with the skin of my teeth,</hi> do obſerve, that the devil left <hi>Job</hi> his mouth whole, that with it he might blaſpheme God, and bewail his calamity: ſo have the Clergy their Learning left them (I will not ſay with <hi>Menippus, Literas habent queis ſibi &amp; fortunae ſuae maledicant</hi>) but to lament their own and the Churches miſery. They are indeed but your words that we hear; and yet they, though <hi>levitèr volant, gravitèr vulnerant:</hi> but if you had power over the Clergy anſwerable to your will, you would quickly give them cauſe to complain in the words of that exiled Poet,
<q>Vix habet in nobis jam nova plaga locum.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The ſum of all I have to ſay concerning your diſcourſe is this: You are a ſcourge in the hand of God, with which he is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to chaſtiſe his Laodicean Angels: under which yet they may behold his favour, on their repentance. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.19. And I beſeech God to give you alſo ſight of your errour, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for it, leſt when the Lord hath done correcting his people, he caſt his rod into the fire of his wrath. Now is their hour of temptation, and now are the powers of darkneſſe prevalent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them; now are they conformed to their Maſter Chriſt in ſuffering, being alſo given into the hands of men who deſpite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully uſe and perſecute them,
<q>— <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </q> But be of good comfort (precious ſouls) for your redemption draweth nigh: <hi>the rod of the wicked ſhall not alwaies reſt on the back of the righteous,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <q>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>—</q> The righteous ſhall have dominion in the morning, when the wicked ſhall be turned into hell.</p>
            <p>I have anſwered your Book no ſooner, becauſe how long ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it hath been extant, it came but lately to my hand, and by the date 1650. I could not think it ſtill unanſwered: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:49844:23"/>otherwiſe informed, I took this task upon my ſelf, for fear you ſhould think it unanſwerable, although men of greater abilities might perhaps diſdain it as unworthy their anſwer. I have herein uſed more frequent interrogations then ſute to the mildeneſſe of my diſpoſition, but I was in part thereto con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained by your negative manner of writing. In the main I deſire to have been ſincere, as in charity I think you to have been in yours; for it's poſſible for a man to think he ſerves God in his greateſt diſſervice. For what infirmities of my own I have herein diſcovered, I deſire not concealment but condo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: for <hi>humanum eſt errare,</hi> in many things we offend all: and
<q>Hanc alijs veniam cupimus dabimuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> viciſſim.</q>
            </p>
            <p>IN your Poſt-ſcript you deny your ſelf to be againſt duty. For anſwer to which I deſire you but to conſider the words of our Saviour Chriſt, where being about to give a cognizance of falſe Prophets, he ſaith, <hi>Ye ſhall know them by their fruits.</hi> What? the fruits of their lives? no doubtleſſe, for then we muſt give the better to divers hereticks, and to many of the preſent Papiſts: but if the fruits of their doctrine be intended, as neceſſarily they muſt, what rotten ſtuff would you feed our ſouls with? no ſpecious Apples of <hi>Aſphaltus</hi> would ſo deceive our taſte, no gliſtering <hi>Cantharides</hi> ſo poyſon our bodies, as this doctrine of devils (in form of Angels of Light) beguile our ſouls. You are not (you ſay) againſt duty: no more was <hi>Pelagius</hi> againſt free-grace, if you will beleeve him: but as he did <hi>Gratiae vocabulo uti ad frangendam invidiam,</hi> ſo do you draw the vail of duty over your irreligious Category, to cover the horridneſſe of your intention. For you clearly ſet your ſelf againſt publique Ordinances, by which we come to the knowledge of our duty, by which we are reproved for omiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and exhorted to performance of our duty: and if <hi>ſublatâ cauſâ tollitur effectus,</hi> let any reaſonable man judge if you be not againſt duty.</p>
            <p>If the publike Miniſtry be the ordinary means of knowing, loving, fearing, and obeying God (as all faithfull ſouls will
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:49844:24"/>witneſſe it to be) then he that would deprive us of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Miniſtry, would rob us of the ordinary means of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, loving, fearing, and obeying God: But you endeavour to deprive us of the former, and <hi>Quod cauſa cauſae eſt cauſa cauſati,</hi> as well in privatives as in poſitives; I abhor to write, and I wiſh you would tremble to think how deeply you are involved in the concluſion.</p>
            <p>And now Sir, If you be not one that doth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, reaſon might perſwade you to acknowledge your errours: and if that glimmering light of it that I can hold forth, how much more thoſe reſplendant raies that proceed from greater Lumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries? But if a ſpirit of deluſion hath poſſeſſed you, and your Gangrene be come to a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>dolendum eſt a medico, quod non delendum medicinâ.</hi> I am in part ſatisfied, as I have in part performed my duty. And having no more to ſay to you, I muſt ſay what remains to God hearing prayers: to whoſe mercy I commit you, and continue, Though the weakeſt oppugner, yet the ſtrongeſt (in deſire at leaſt) deteſter of your errours,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:49844:24"/>
            <head>TO THE LOVER OF THE CLERGY <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> M. <hi>JOHN DAVY</hi> OF <hi>Taunton Magdalen,</hi> Perſeverance.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have ſent you in theſe Papers a Salve, which by Gods bleſſing on your coſt and direction I was able to compoſe for that wound which an undeſerved enemy hath made on the reputation of the Clergy: a wound too deep for me to ſearch, too great to cure: but having found one inſtrument that cauſed it where I now reſide, I have endeavoured to apply my medicine thereto, hoping that (as is belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of the <hi>Unguentum armarium</hi>) it may tranſmit ſome ſanative vertue to th'affected ſubject. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, I ſhall hereby manifeſt my reſpect unto the ſuffering Parties, and (in ſome meaſure) have performed the duty of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your most obſervant Nephew, and ever gratefull ſervant, <hi>J.D.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <p>The Authour of <hi>The Clergy in their Colours</hi> (of which this is an Anſwer) was for publiſhing the ſame, expel'd the Houſe, and his Book ordered to be burnt.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:49844:25"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:49844:25"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
